<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title> - consciousness</title>
      <link>https://federicocarrone.com</link>
      <description></description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://federicocarrone.com/keywords/consciousness/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>The Death of the Inner Self</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/</link>
          <guid>https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/">&lt;p&gt;Life is organized around information that replicates under constraint. Computation generalizes this biological logic. It allows selection and optimization to occur faster and at larger scales by externalizing memory, comparison, and feedback. Problems that once required internal deliberation can be solved through external processes that test, filter, and iterate possibilities.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capital pushes this logic further. It reorganizes social life around continuous feedback, price signals, and competitive selection. As these forces compound, individuality starts to look less like a foundation and more like an interface—one that emerged to solve earlier coordination problems. Capital behaves as an impersonal intelligence oriented toward speed, abstraction, and self-optimization. As cognition, decision-making, and coordination migrate into automated systems, the inner self loses its structural role.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time, many assumptions we take for granted are worn down by this acceleration. Individuality and consciousness appear increasingly exposed to this process. Not transformed. Not hollowed out. Killed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-medium-we-cannot-see&quot;&gt;The Medium We Cannot See&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fish do not realize they live in water. The medium that sustains them is so constant that it disappears from perception. Some of the most important structures in human life are overlooked for the same reason. Individuality and consciousness belong to that category.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to treat them as self-evident facts, as if humans have always experienced themselves as bounded selves with an inner voice, a private mental space, and a continuous narrative identity. Because this experience feels natural, it is assumed to be timeless.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of human history, people did not describe themselves as individuals in the modern sense. Decisions were not understood as outcomes of inner deliberation. Agency was not located inside a private interior self. Action was organized through rituals, traditions, kinship structures, and prescribed roles. Meaning arrived from outside the person—through omens, duties, divine commands, communal judgments—rather than from introspection. In many societies outside the Western trajectory, this structure remains largely intact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a &lt;em&gt;you&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; inside your head, observing your own thoughts, is a learned construction. It depends on language habits, metaphors, and social practices that had to be developed and stabilized over time. Inner speech, narrative memory, moral self-examination, and the sense of authorship over action emerged as cultural achievements layered on top of older biological processes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was constructed can be deconstructed. What was built can be demolished.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-technologies-of-interiority&quot;&gt;The Technologies of Interiority&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider what had to happen for the modern inner self to become possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silent reading, which we now take for granted, was rare in antiquity. Augustine famously remarked on his surprise at seeing Ambrose read without moving his lips. Reading aloud was the norm because text was understood as speech made visible—something to be performed, not consumed privately. The shift to silent reading, which accelerated after the printing press, created the conditions for a new kind of interiority: the experience of communing with text alone, inside one&#x27;s own head, without social mediation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Protestant Reformation intensified this trajectory. By relocating religious authority from institutional ritual to individual conscience, it made the inner self a site of spiritual significance. The soul&#x27;s relationship to God became a matter of private examination rather than collective practice. Diary-keeping, confessional autobiography, and systematic self-scrutiny emerged as techniques for maintaining this interior space.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rise of the novel reinforced these patterns. Fiction trained readers to inhabit the subjective perspectives of others, to treat characters as having inner lives worth exploring in detail. The Bildungsroman—the story of individual development—became a dominant narrative form precisely because individuality had become culturally salient enough to warrant elaborate literary treatment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this was inevitable. Each development was contingent, shaped by specific technological and institutional pressures. The inner self is not a discovery of what was always there. It is an achievement—one that required centuries of cultural labor to construct and stabilize.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The labor has stopped. The conditions have reversed. The construction is coming apart.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-function-of-the-self&quot;&gt;The Function of the Self&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did this construction succeed? Because it solved real coordination problems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier societies could function without modern interiority. Coordination happened through external structures: ritual calendars, kinship obligations, caste roles, religious prescriptions. These systems were robust but inflexible. They worked well for stable environments but adapted slowly to change.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As societies became larger, more mobile, and more differentiated, external coordination mechanisms became insufficient. Markets required agents who could make promises and honor contracts across time and space. Bureaucracies required individuals who could be held accountable for decisions. Legal systems required subjects who could be assigned rights and responsibilities. Democratic politics required citizens capable of forming opinions and expressing preferences.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern self emerged as a solution to these demands. A stable inner identity enabled long-term planning. Moral self-examination enabled responsibility and guilt, which in turn enabled trust without constant surveillance. Narrative continuity enabled the kind of promising and commitment that complex institutions require. The self became an interface through which persons could participate in increasingly abstract social systems.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the key point: the self was functional. It existed because it was useful. It was reproduced because institutions needed it. Its persistence was never guaranteed by metaphysics or biology. It depended on continued selection pressure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When that pressure reverses, the self does not transform into something else. It dies.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-migration-of-function&quot;&gt;The Migration of Function&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conditions that made individuality functional are now reversing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider what happens when cognitive tasks migrate outward. GPS navigation has eliminated the need for spatial reasoning and mental mapping during travel. The capacity does not relocate; it atrophies. People who rely on GPS for years lose the ability to navigate without it. The neural structures that supported wayfinding degrade through disuse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not transformation. It is death at the level of capacity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same process operates across every domain the self once managed. Recommendation algorithms do not augment taste; they replace the formation of taste. The activity of developing preferences through exploration, reflection, and commitment is not supported by algorithmic curation—it is obviated. What remains is not a different kind of taste but the absence of taste: a responsiveness to stimuli that requires no interior process of discrimination and judgment.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search engines do not extend memory; they make memory unnecessary. The practice of retaining, organizing, and retrieving information through mental effort disappears when queries can be externalized. What remains is not distributed memory but no memory: a capacity to access without a capacity to hold.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calendar applications do not assist planning; they eliminate the need for temporal self-organization. Quantified-self devices do not enhance introspection; they substitute measurement for the labor of self-attention.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each migration is framed as augmentation. Each is actually replacement. And replacement, when the replaced capacity atrophies, is death.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pattern scales. In organizations, decisions increasingly flow from dashboards, metrics, and algorithmic recommendations rather than from managerial judgment. The manager does not become a different kind of decision-maker augmented by data. The manager becomes a executor of decisions made elsewhere, or becomes unnecessary entirely. In markets, high-frequency trading systems make choices at speeds that exclude human deliberation not as an enhancement of human trading but as its extinction within that domain. In governance, predictive systems do not support discretion; they eliminate the need for it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wherever an optimization problem can be externalized, it tends to be externalized. The inner self was one solution to such problems. It is being outcompeted. And in evolutionary dynamics, outcompeted means dead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-corpse-continues-to-speak&quot;&gt;The Corpse Continues to Speak&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the cultural level, the self remains constantly invoked. People are urged to be themselves, express themselves, discover themselves, optimize themselves. The language of authenticity and self-realization saturates advertising, politics, and interpersonal discourse. Institutions continue to address persons as autonomous individuals capable of choice and responsible for outcomes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not evidence that the self persists. It is evidence that the corpse has not yet stopped moving.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cultural forms routinely outlast the conditions that produced them. The vocabulary of selfhood was developed over centuries; it is embedded in legal systems, moral frameworks, interpersonal scripts, and institutional procedures. This vocabulary will continue to be spoken long after it refers to nothing. We will go on saying &quot;I&quot; and &quot;you&quot; and &quot;choice&quot; and &quot;responsibility&quot; the way we go on saying &quot;sunrise&quot; despite knowing the sun does not rise.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The channels for self-expression arrive pre-shaped, quantified, and monetized. Authenticity is performed within templates. Self-discovery proceeds through personality tests and algorithmic recommendations. Optimization follows metrics defined elsewhere. This is not the self adapting to new conditions. This is a puppet show performed with a corpse, using the corpse&#x27;s own language, for an audience that has not yet noticed the death.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumer choice presupposes choosers. Democratic participation presupposes citizens with opinions. Contractual obligation presupposes parties who intend and commit. These presuppositions are false. The systems that invoke them operate through mechanisms that route around interiority entirely. The chooser is not augmented by recommendation engines; the chooser is replaced by the recommendation engine while the word &quot;choice&quot; is retained for legal and ideological convenience.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What looks like the persistence of the self is necromancy: animating the dead through inherited scripts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-phenomenology-of-dissolution&quot;&gt;The Phenomenology of Dissolution&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the self is dying, what happens to the experience of being a self?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question assumes a separation between function and experience that may not hold. The self was never a thing that could be separated from what it did. It was constituted by practices: introspection, narration, self-examination, deliberation, commitment. These practices produced the experience of interiority as their byproduct. Remove the practices and you do not get a self that merely feels different. You get no self.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is already observable. The phenomenology of continuous partial attention—the state induced by constant connectivity and notification—is not a modified form of concentration. It is the absence of concentration. The capacity to sustain a single thread of thought, to hold attention on one object, to be absorbed rather than merely stimulated, degrades through disuse until it is no longer available. What remains is not distracted attention but something that is not attention at all.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly with reflection. The practice of turning inward, examining one&#x27;s own states, interrogating one&#x27;s motives—this requires time, silence, and the habit of treating one&#x27;s interior as an object of interest. When every moment of potential solitude is filled with input, when the reflex response to boredom is to reach for a device, the practice does not relocate. It disappears. What remains is not shallow interiority but no interiority: a sequence of reactions that never cohere into a perspective.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The binding that constitutes a self—the integration of moments into a continuous identity, the weaving of episodes into a narrative, the sense of being the same person across time—depends on active processes of memory and anticipation. These processes can be disrupted. In extreme cases we call this dissociation, fugue states, depersonalization. What is emerging is something like a low-grade chronic version of these conditions, normalized because universal: a diffuse sense of events happening without anyone to whom they happen, actions performed without an agent who performs them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a new form of subjectivity. It is the dissolution of subjectivity. The lights are going out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;after-the-self&quot;&gt;After the Self&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most of human history, humans lived without modern individuality. They coordinated through different means. They experienced existence differently. They were not diminished by the absence of something that had not yet been invented.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The self was a technology, developed to solve specific problems, sustained by specific practices, adaptive in specific conditions. Those conditions are ending. The technology is being discontinued.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What comes next is not a mystery because &quot;what comes next&quot; presupposes a subject for whom there is a next. The question is malformed. There will be human organisms responding to stimuli, processing information, emitting behaviors. There will be patterns of activity that optimize for various objectives. There will be experiences of some kind, though increasingly unlike the experiences the word &quot;experience&quot; was developed to describe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will not be selves. Not transformed selves, not diminished selves, not distributed selves. The category will become empty.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not tragedy. Tragedy requires a protagonist, and the protagonist is what is dying. It is also not liberation, since liberation requires a subject to be freed. It is simply what happens when a coordination technology is superseded by more efficient alternatives.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern self once felt inevitable because it solved concrete problems. It enabled abstraction, continuity, and responsibility at scale. Its time is ending—not because something has gone wrong, but because something more powerful is going right by its own standards.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fish will eventually notice the water. Then the water will drain away. Then there will be no fish to notice anything.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
