<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title> - consciousness</title>
      <link>https://federicocarrone.com</link>
      <description></description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://federicocarrone.com/keywords/consciousness/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>The Death of the Inner Self</title>
          <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/</link>
          <guid>https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://federicocarrone.com/articles/the-death-of-the-inner-self/">&lt;p&gt;I am working on a series of articles that connect biology, computation, philosophy, the history of the West and the formation of individuality. The core argument is simple: many features of human life that appear stable and natural are historically produced. As society accelerates a number of these features begin to lose their function and their permanence. This is just a draft of what I&#x27;m working on.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is organized around information that replicates under constraint. Computation generalizes this biological logic. It allows selection and optimization to occur faster and at larger scales by externalizing memory comparison and feedback. Problems that once required internal deliberation can be solved through external processes that test filter and iterate possibilities. Capital pushes this logic further. It reorganizes social life around continuous feedback price signals and competitive selection. As these forces compound individuality starts to look less like a foundation and more like an interface that emerged to solve earlier coordination problems. Capital behaves as an impersonal intelligence oriented toward speed abstraction and self optimization. As cognition decision making and coordination migrate into automated systems the inner self loses its structural role.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over time many assumptions we take for granted are worn down by this acceleration. Individuality and consciousness appear increasingly exposed to this process.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The death of the inner self and individuality&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fish do not realize they live in water. The medium that sustains them is so constant that it disappears from perception. Some of the most important structures are overlooked for the same reason. Individuality and consciousness belong to that category.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to treat individuality and consciousness as self evident facts. As if humans have always experienced themselves as bounded selves with an inner voice a private mental space and a continuous narrative identity. Because this experience feels natural it is assumed to be timeless. However for most of human history people did not describe themselves as individuals in the modern sense. Decisions were not understood as outcomes of inner deliberation and agency was not located inside a private interior self. Action was organized through rituals traditions, kinship and prescribed roles. Meaning arrived from outside the person rather than from introspection. In many societies outside the Western trajectory this structure remains largely intact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of a you inside your head observing your own thoughts is therefore a learned construction. It depends on language habits metaphors and social practices that had to be developed and stabilized over time. Inner speech narrative memory moral self examination and the sense of authorship over action emerged as cultural achievements layered on top of older biological processes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern societies actively reproduce this configuration. From early childhood people are trained to understand themselves as autonomous units with opinions preferences goals and an inner life that belongs only to them. The training is so pervasive that it becomes invisible. Other ways of being human recede from view even though many have existed and some still persist.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conditions that once made individuality functional are weakening. Earlier systems relied on human subjects to think decide judge and take responsibility. Cognition and coordination were constrained by human minds. Individuality emerged as a solution. A stable self enabled long term planning moral accounting and institutional continuity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earlier societies coordinated without modern consciousness. Contemporary systems increasingly coordinate without modern selves. Decision making proceeds without inner deliberation. Meaning is delivered through incentives metrics and feedback loops. At the cultural level individuality remains constantly invoked. People are urged to be themselves express themselves optimize themselves. Yet the channels for expression arrive pre shaped quantified and monetized. What appears as selfhood increasingly takes the form of managed performance within narrow bounds.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern self once felt inevitable because it solved concrete problems. It enabled abstraction continuity and responsibility at scale. Its future usefulness is far less certain.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
