<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title> - coordination</title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://federicocarrone.com/keywords/coordination/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://federicocarrone.com"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://federicocarrone.com/keywords/coordination/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>On the displacement of trust: proving, verification and the reconfiguration of authority</title>
        <published>2023-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-04-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://federicocarrone.com/articles/on-the-displacement-of-trust-proving-verification-and-the-reconfiguration-of-authority/"/>
        <id>https://federicocarrone.com/articles/on-the-displacement-of-trust-proving-verification-and-the-reconfiguration-of-authority/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://federicocarrone.com/articles/on-the-displacement-of-trust-proving-verification-and-the-reconfiguration-of-authority/">&lt;p&gt;Moments of genuine scientific and conceptual transformation rarely announce themselves clearly at the time they occur, not because they lack importance, but because they do not arrive as finished doctrines or named revolutions. They emerge instead as quiet accumulations of tools and techniques forged under pressure, usually in response to systems that no longer scale and assumptions that continue to operate long after they have ceased to be true. Only much later do such developments appear inevitable, and only in retrospect do we recognize that what once looked like narrow technical progress was in fact a deeper reconfiguration of how societies organize knowledge, authority, and trust.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are living through such a moment now. Contemporary society depends on vast digital systems that coordinate billions of people across markets, governments, media, and infrastructure, yet the models of trust that allow these systems to function were designed for a world that was slower, more legible, and far more centralized. Institutions, platforms, and intermediaries remain charged with certifying truth, protecting privacy, and enforcing rules, even as information moves at speeds and scales that overwhelm human oversight and strain institutional capacity beyond repair. The resulting tension is not merely inefficiency or lag, but a structural mismatch between how coordination actually occurs and how legitimacy is still supposed to be produced.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the center of this mismatch lies a problem that is epistemic rather than technological. We increasingly lack reliable ways to know what is true, who can be trusted, and whether systems behave as they claim to behave. Data can be copied, altered, and fabricated at negligible cost. Decisions that shape lives, markets, and public outcomes are delegated to systems whose internal logic is opaque even to their operators. Participation in economic and social life routinely requires the surrender of personal information without any meaningful ability to verify how it will be used, retained, or recombined. Trust has become simultaneously indispensable and structurally fragile, demanded everywhere and grounded nowhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Historically, societies managed this problem through social mechanisms such as reputation, kinship, ritual, and later through institutions grounded in law, bureaucracy, and professional authority. These arrangements worked not because they were perfect, but because power and information were scarce, slow moving, and costly to manipulate. Verification could be mediated by human judgment, and failure propagated slowly enough to be absorbed. In the digital era, trust has been increasingly outsourced to large platforms whose incentives are aligned with scale, growth, and engagement rather than durability, legitimacy, or accountability. The widening gap between institutional claims and individual verifiability is not a temporary failure of governance, but a structural consequence of this arrangement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new set of ideas has begun to challenge this foundation, not by proposing better oversight, more transparency reports, or more ethical intermediaries, but by questioning the role of trust itself. Instead of asking users, citizens, or counterparties to believe claims or defer to authority, these systems aim to make claims provable. Truth in this framework is not asserted, negotiated, or enforced through institutional standing, but demonstrated through structure. This is a subtle but profound shift, because it displaces the locus of credibility from who speaks to what can be shown.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most unintuitive aspects of this shift is the possibility of proving that a statement is true without revealing the information that underlies it. In most social and institutional contexts, proof has always been inseparable from disclosure. To prove eligibility, one presents documents. To prove compliance, one exposes records. To prove correctness, one reveals the method. This coupling between proof and exposure has shaped how power, surveillance, and authority operate for centuries, and it has quietly normalized the idea that access is the price of participation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zero knowledge proofs break this coupling. They allow a person or a system to demonstrate that a condition holds without revealing anything beyond the fact that it does. The verifier learns that the claim is valid, but gains no access to identities, histories, or underlying data. For decades, this capability remained confined to theory, inhabiting a domain cryptographers half derisively referred to as moon math, techniques so distant from practical deployment that they appeared to exist in a separate universe from working systems. The mathematics was sound, but the computational costs were prohibitive. Advances in proof systems, algorithms, and hardware have compressed proving times to generate the proof from days eo minutes, transforming what was once an intellectual curiosity into a viable infrastructural primitive.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this shift takes hold, familiar problems begin to reorder themselves, especially those embedded in the foundations of institutional power. Consider record keeping and identity verification, among the oldest mechanisms through which states, banks, and markets establish continuity, legitimacy, and control. Modern economic life depends on vast registries of personal data collected to satisfy requirements such as know your customer, anti money laundering, accreditation, residency, and eligibility. These records are duplicated across banks, regulators, employers, and platforms, producing enormous storage costs, constant compliance friction, and an expanding surface for abuse, leakage, and surveillance. Individuals are repeatedly required to disclose the same documents, even when the underlying facts they are meant to establish remain unchanged for years.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A zero knowledge proof reorganizes this arrangement at its root. Instead of preserving and circulating copies of passports, bank statements, employment histories, and transaction records, an individual can prove that a condition is satisfied without revealing the data used to establish it. A bank does not need to store identity documents to know that a customer meets regulatory requirements. A counterparty does not need access to financial history to verify solvency or eligibility. What persists is not an accumulating archive of sensitive records, but a cryptographic guarantee that a rule was satisfied at a given moment under agreed constraints. Record keeping shifts from the indefinite preservation of personal data to the preservation of verifiable facts, introducing a model of institutional memory that retains compliance without retaining exposure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same logic applies to the growing crisis of synthetic media. As generated text, images, and video saturate the information environment, the question of whether a human produced a given artifact becomes undecidable by inspection. Provenance can no longer be inferred from appearance. Zero knowledge proofs offer an alternative architecture in which content carries cryptographic attestation of its origin, proof that a specific model operating under defined constraints generated it, or that a verified human identity signed it. Where audiences once relied on institutional trust, the artifact itself can now carry a verifiable history. Institutions do not disappear, but their authority becomes conditional, constrained by structures that can be independently audited.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second development addresses a different vulnerability of digital life, namely the assumption that data must be exposed in order to be useful. Nearly all contemporary computation requires information to be readable by the systems that process it, leading to massive concentrations of sensitive data and transforming privacy into a matter of policy, compliance, and promise rather than architecture. Protection occurs after exposure, through regulation and penalties, rather than before exposure, through design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fully homomorphic encryption proposes a different arrangement. It allows computation to take place directly on encrypted data, such that information remains unreadable at every stage of processing while still producing correct results. Systems operate on data they cannot see. Databases are queried without revealing records. Machine learning models train on inputs that are never decrypted. This reverses a foundational assumption of digital infrastructure by making exposure unnecessary for utility rather than unavoidable.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like zero knowledge proofs, fully homomorphic encryption spent years confined to theoretical possibility, its computational overhead rendering it impractical outside laboratories. That constraint is now loosening as algorithmic improvements and specialized hardware bring encrypted computation within reach of production systems. When these two capabilities are considered together, a broader pattern emerges. Systems can verify correctness without learning inputs and can compute without accessing underlying data. Participation no longer requires disclosure by default. Industries built on the assumption that access to data is the price of service face a structural challenge, not from regulation or cultural pressure, but from technical alternatives that make the tradeoff itself obsolete.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The regulatory implications are immediate and uncomfortable. Online gambling, programmatic advertising, and algorithmic trading all operate in domains where incentives to deceive are strong and oversight is limited. Traditional enforcement relies either on trusting operators or demanding intrusive access to proprietary systems. Zero knowledge proofs combined with encrypted computation introduce a third option in which firms demonstrate compliance on encrypted data without revealing competitive intelligence or user information. Audits become cryptographic rather than bureaucratic, shifting power away from discretion and toward constraint. It weakens certain institutional roles even as it strengthens the credibility of outcomes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final element of this transformation concerns coordination itself. Complex societies depend on shared records, shared rules, and shared reality, and historically this has required centralized authorities to maintain consistency and resolve disputes. Distributed systems approach this problem differently, allowing independent participants to agree on outcomes without reliance on a single trusted actor. Bitcoin demonstrated that monetary coordination could occur without central banks or payment processors, with correctness enforced by re executing every transaction across the network. This eliminated trust, but at the cost of scale. Re execution does not scale indefinitely. Verification remained coupled to execution. Zero knowledge proofs break this coupling. A single machine executes a computation and produces a proof, while verification becomes cheap, fast, and widely accessible. The blockchain evolves from a slow distributed computer into a verification layer, less an engine that performs work than a court that evaluates proofs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In places where inflation and institutional decay have eroded confidence in traditional finance, such systems already function as daily infrastructure. Stable value moves through phones and informal markets not as ideology but as necessity. The unresolved question is not whether permissionless coordination works under conditions of collapse, but whether it generalizes to societies experiencing fatigue rather than failure, where institutions still function but no longer command belief.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These systems are not without risk. Cryptographic bugs have drained enormous sums. Proof systems rely on assumptions and implementations that have not yet faced decades of adversarial pressure. Verification relocates trust rather than abolishing it, shifting it from institutions and individuals to mathematics, code, and hardware, each with its own failure modes. What is changing is not the existence of trust, but its distribution and visibility.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zero knowledge proofs, encrypted computation, and distributed coordination are no longer isolated research agendas but components of an emerging stack. Verification is becoming cheap. Privacy preserving computation is becoming practical. Coordination without centralized trust is becoming robust. These shifts arrive as artificial intelligence makes fabrication cheap and pervasive, rendering persuasion, credentials, and authority increasingly brittle. In such an environment, structure becomes the only guarantee that scales.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Institutions do not disappear, but their role is unsettled. They shift from being sources of trust to operators within systems that are verifiable by design. Authority becomes constrained rather than assumed. This transition is neither purely technical nor purely political. It alters what it means to claim, to comply, and to coordinate. What is taking shape is not simply a new set of tools, but a different condition for social life, one in which legitimacy is no longer anchored primarily in who speaks, but in what can be proven, and in which trust, once the silent center of coordination, is displaced, redistributed, and no longer guaranteed to return to the place it once occupied.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
